<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The copies of severall letters contrary to the opinion of the present powers, presented to the Lord Gen. Fairfax, and Lieut. Gen. Cromwell. By Francis White, Maior of his Excellencies regiment of foot.</title>
            <author>White, Francis, d. 1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96342</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1764</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E548_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204063</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863773</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863773</idno>
            <idno type="VID">164983</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96342)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 164983)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 85:E548[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The copies of severall letters contrary to the opinion of the present powers, presented to the Lord Gen. Fairfax, and Lieut. Gen. Cromwell. By Francis White, Maior of his Excellencies regiment of foot.</title>
                  <author>White, Francis, d. 1657.</author>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
                  <author>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Paine for Tho. Slater, and Stephen Bowtell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 20 1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:164983:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE COPIES of Severall LETTERS Contrary to the opinion of the preſent powers, Preſented to the Lord Gen. Fairfax, AND <hi>LIE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T. GEN. CROMWELL.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Francis White,</hi> Maior of his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies Regiment of Foot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Paine</hi> for <hi>Tho. Slater,</hi> and <hi>Stephen Bowtell.</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:164983:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:164983:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>HAving for ſome yeares been an Actor in the Affaires of the late warres, and likewiſe an obſerver of the proceedings of State, in which I have been concerned more then every private perſon; I have therefore, offered my Judgement, and declared my opinion in matters of higheſt concernment to my Lord Generall, and Lievt. Gen. <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and had no great deſire to have publiſhed what I have written: But hearing by many of my friends, that it is generally reported by moſt that have heard of me, that I have now declined my principles, and am turned Cavalier. The reaſon of this Conception is, becauſe J declared my Diſcent to the taking away the life of the King: But to manifeſt to the world, the truth and innocency of my heart, J have publiſhed theſe following Letters, to ſhew that J was of the ſame Judgement formerly as J now continue, as may appear in my Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſent to Lievt. Gen. <hi>Cromwell,</hi> almoſt a yeare agoe, and what J have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to my Lord Generall, although contrary to the opinion of the preſent powers; J thought my ſelf bound in Conſcience to performe, to preſerve my own inward peace. For although ſome men make no conſcience of their Ingagements, Vowes, and Oaths, yet J hope, God will give me power rather to ſuffer death, then deſtroy my life. J know that my Judgement is not infallible, yet notwithſtanding J muſt keep cloſe to my Principles, untill J am convinced of Error; J have here decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my Principles and purpoſe, to ſtand in the proſecution of the publique ſervice with faithfulneſſe, whiles God by his grace doth inable me.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Francis White.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>March the 20. 1648.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:164983:3"/>
            <head>The Copie of a Letter preſented to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> Generall.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am a Member of your Army, and included in all actions done by the Diſciplinary power, whiles I ſilently conſent thereto, and I would never appear a Diſcenter to any thing that tends to publick good, although never ſo prejudiciall to my particular intereſt; but rather then I would ſubmit to any thing of eſſentiall publick preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to the people, or to deſtroy my inward peace, I would expoſe my ſelf to a temporall deſtruction. For God is my witneſſe, I do not ſo much fear them that can kil the body onely, as I do him that is able to caſt both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and ſoul into hell; ſo farre as I have been imployed in the common work, I have chearfully acted or born my publick teſtimonies, and I hope for ever ſhall. My Lord, I have taken notice of many Petitions from almoſt all the Forces in <hi>England,</hi> and from divers people of the Countreys, which ſupplicate for many good things, which they deſire your Excellency to procure. In all which good things, I do heartily concur with their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but I have obſerved this as one thing generally deſired, that they may have execution of Juſtice upon the King, and as far as I can perceive, it is generally intended by the Officers of the Army, and the Members of the preſent Houſe of Commons, to take away the life of the King. But with ſubmiſſion to your Excellency, I deſire leave to declare my diſcent, and upon grounds conſcientious for theſe Reaſons following.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, Becauſe there are no clear grounds by any Legall Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to take away the life of the King.</item>
               <item>Secondly, It is contrary to our firſt Ingagement, and our generall Profeſſions, Vows, and Covenants, to God and the world.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, I do not diſcern it will produce any generall good to the Nation, but rather the contrary.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Having declared my opinion, and the chief Reaſons for the ſame, I deſire your Lordſhip to read theſe following Lines, for the clearing of thoſe Reaſons, and the juſtifying my integritie and innocency in former actings.</p>
            <p>At the firſt taking up of Arms, I was ſenſible of the oppreſſion and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice which was exerciſed by the King and his Miniſters upon the people; he exalting himſelf to act beyond all Laws, which his Predeceſſors and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:164983:3"/>himſelf had bound themſelves by conſent to obſerve; He raiſing Arms to inforce the exerciſe of his power, to the maintaining an abſolute tyranny over the Nation, was the chief ground of my oppoſing him: and I have freely acted in the affairs of War, to the ſubduing of his power, and the vindicating of the peoples juſt Rights, and claim to the diſpoſall of the Military power without his conſent. In the proſecution of this ſervice, I have been as free from ſeeking revenge upon the Perſon of the King, as to violate my own life. The chief end I ſeek, is the preſervation of the righteous people, with the ſafetie and well being of the whole, and if poſſible without taking away the life of <hi>Charles Steward,</hi> King of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt I ſay, I do not underſtand how it may be done by any Legall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority according to the Kingly Government, though it may be a juſt thing, yet I know not how it may juſtly be done. I never heard of any Throne erected in the earth, either by God or men, for the judging of a King, untill the erecting of this late tribunall at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> All the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Seats, that are legally erected in this Nation, were made by King, Lords, and Commons; but the King ever did exempt himſelf from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall judgement, by vertue of the Military, Regall, and Legiſlative power which he retained in himſelf, which was gotten by the Sword of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, and kept by Traditionall diſſent: although the people ſince the Conqueſt, have had the libertie of chooſing Laws, ſo that he did not ſet up Laws and Judicatures legally at his will, yet there was no Law made, nor Judicatures erected, but by his will, although he agreed, the people ſhould have the power of chooſing Laws, yet he determined, that he would keep the power of confirming Laws; ſo that no Law was ever made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his will.</p>
            <p>And if it be throughly examined; we may finde that the King hath no other right to the Military, Regall, and Legiſlative power, then the Sword did conſtitute and inveſt him with by divine permiſſion, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſubmitting thereto for fear, and to avoid greateſt miſchief. But now the King and his partie being conquered by the Sword, I beleeve the Sword may juſtly remove the power from him, and ſettle it in its origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall fountain next under God, the people. But to judge or execute his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I do not underſtand any Legall Authority in being can juſtly do it. I doubt not but the Sword may do it, but how righteous judgement that may be, that God and future generations will judge. It is clear that the Military power is exalted above the Regall and Legiſlative power, and is now come to the throne of God, and under no other Legall Judgement,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:164983:4"/>untill there be a Legall Authority erected, as is offered in the Agreement, to which it may ſubmit. And ſeeing God hath in righteouſneſſe for the ſins of the people, and their King, brought us into this unhappie conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I therefore plead with your Excellency, to uſe the ſword with as much tenderneſſe as may be, to preſerve the lives of men, and eſpecially the life of the King.</p>
            <p>And for my ſecond reaſon, Becauſe we have made generall profeſſion of preſerving his perſon, and whenſoever any accuſed us of ſeeking the life of the King, we alwayes denyed it, untill this late Remonſtrance. Now Sir, it is as reall a manifeſtation of a Chriſtian, a honourable and noble ſpirit, as can be diſcovered to the world, to be true to what it doth profeſſe, and to be the ſame in adverſitie, as in proſperity, and in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as it was in adverſitie; and it is more honourable to ſave the life of a conquered enemie, then to deſtroy him: For if he hath proſecuted his deſignes according to his judgement and conſcience, and were in the wrong way, it was becauſe God ſuffered the Devill to blind his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that he did not know the truth, and it is better to let him live, and learne to repent, then to make haſt to ſend him to deſtruction; ſo that his remaining alive, be not any generall prejudice, or more miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous then his death would be, which would well be conſidered under the third reaſon.</p>
            <p>I doe not underſtand any eſſentiall good can acrew to the people, by the taking away his life. For it is not ſo much the perſon that can hurt us, as the power that is made up in the Kingly office by this corrupt conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for if the perſon be taken away preſently, another layeth claime to the Kingly Office, and for any thing I know, hath as much right to the Dominion as his Prediceſſor had, and will, queſtionleſſe, have all the aſſiſtance that this perſon can procure, for the attaining thereof, and will be able to doe more miſchiefe, becauſe he is at liberty, and this under your power.</p>
            <p>Againe, This King being the King of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> according to the Lawes in being, they have an intereſt in his perſon as well as <hi>England,</hi> notwithſtanding he is under our power. Now if you will iudge the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> in that which concernes their intereſt, where you can claime no right, it is a evident wrong, and may give them iuſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and ground of quarrell againſt this Nation, and by this, may be of more preiudice to the whole, then can be good to the particular. I deſire my Lord, that we may iſſue a Chriſtian ſpirit, not rendring evill for evill, but rather good for evill. Although wicked men will deale wickedly with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:164983:4"/>us, yet let us deale mercifully with them, and pardon and forgive, as wee deſire God ſhould pardon and forgive us. Jn this way J doe verily beleeve we ſhall be greater Conquerers then yet we have been, if we can conquer ourſelves, and the affection of our enemies which this doth lead unto. My Lord, in all that I have written, J am not againſt the judging of the King; but J ſay it is by no legall Authority, but only what the Sword exalteth: although it be not an exact Marſhal Court, yet it is little different, and not a Legitimate Authority to the King, yet it may as iuſtly iudge him, as ever he iudged the people, and may dethrone him, and diveſt him of all power and authority in the Engliſh Nation. And I thinke it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſo far to proceed, and to detaine him as a priſoner at war, till hee may be delivered with ſafety to yourſelves and the Nation. I deſire your Excellencies favourable Conſtruction of what I have written, and if it be not your Excellencies iudgement, all that I deſire for my ſatisfaction is; That your Excellency will appoint ſuch a Generall Councel as the Army in theſe parts ſhall be included by the Maior voice thereof, if it be not concluded according to my Judgement, yet therein ſhall I have my deſire, becauſe J conſent to be included by the Maior part, to avoid diviſion: If this may not be granted, then muſt I declare my diſcent, and that it is an action done by vertue of the Diſciplinary power of the Army, by which J am not in this caſe willingly included, and ſo I hope I ſhall preſerve my ſelf in innocency and peace, and not be an inſtrument of the miſchiefs, and evils that may be brought upon this Nation, by the taking away the blood of their King. Having taken this Freedom to write to your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, I ſhall now take my leave, and remain.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble Servant, <hi>Francis White.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>January</hi> the 22. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:164983:5"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, His Excellency, the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> Generall.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have for theſe ſix yeers been a ſervant to the publick in the affairs of the late Warce, and for the moſt part under Your Excellencies conduct; and I can ſpeak it with confidence, that no man hath been more faithfull to the people, or to your Lordſhip, in the proſecution of their intereſt, then my ſelf. If I have erred in this work, it hath been chiefly in too forward actings for the publick good; and I would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther erre in the proſecution of my principles with zeal, then in the abuſing patience with ſloath, wherein I am convinced of offence, from which no man is free, I ſhall ſubmit; but rather then betray innocencie with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardice, I would periſh. My Lord, I muſt needs inform you, that my prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples leads me to a concurrence with thoſe people which joyned in the late Petition of the many thouſands in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and parts ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent, and muſt upon all lawfull occaſions, as I will vindicate my inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, uſe means for the accompliſhing of the moſt eſſentiall parts of that Petition; and if the proſecution of ſuch principles be offenſive to your ſelf, as to produce your Lordſhips prejudice, for to remain under your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies diſpleaſure in my imployment, as I am informed from ſome in neer relation to your Excellencie, I do; and that it hath been the reaſon of your Honors depriving me of a further truſt, by putting another over me, to command your Excellencies Regiment, which I had ſought and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted through the greateſt difficult with ſucceſſe, and free from imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or proving falſe to my truſt in the leaſt. If it be true that your Honor bears prejudice to me for my principles, then muſt I in faithfulneſſe ſpeak it, I would rather quit my imployment, then remain under your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips diſaffection and jealouſie in my command: my Lord, I am very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of my diſcouragement, and intreat your Excellency, to give me the manifeſtation of your affection, and acceptance for the future; or to let me know if it may not be, that I may remove my ſelf from being a burden to your Honors proceedings. However I ſhall prove my ſelf to be,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble Servant, Francis White.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Knausburgh,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Septem:</hi> 23. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:164983:5"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Lievt. Gen. <hi>Cromwell.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>JT is not unknown to many, your great pains, and unwearied in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours in the publique imployment, from the firſt undertaking; you have appeared conſtant, valiant, and ſucceſſful in the greateſt affaires of the late war. And having through Gods bleſſing paſſed through many difficults, ſubduing all adverſaties that oppoſed our juſt proceedings It now lieth upon you, and others of the like intereſt, to ſee the eſtabliſhment of thoſe things which we have contended for that there may be ſome requitall for the expence of ſo much Treaſure and Blood. It hath ever been the conſideration of all wiſe undertakers of a war, Firſt, to conſider the right of their cauſe Secondly, their abilities to mannage the ſame. And thirdly, that the benefits may countervail the ill convenience or prejudice, that may be ſuſtained in the procuring ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>What bondage oppreſſion and injuſtice, we were made ſubject to, by the King and his Miniſters; is not unknown to your ſelfe: and when he could no longer keepe the people in ſubjection, under his oppreſſive go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, but was in danger of being caſt out of his Throne he then cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Parliament, which he indeavoured to make ſubject to his will. For the better proſecution of his principles, but failing of his expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Councell, he indeavoured to bring his purpoſes to paſſe, by the force of the ſword, and undertooke the managing a Warr againſt the Parliament, They ſeeing the evill he endeavoured to bring upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and the Nation, tooke courage to appeare faithfull to thoſe who had intruſted them, and called in all that had bowels of mercy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to themſelves or the Nation to come in to the helpe of a diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed State, and to maintaine their juſt rights and freedomes.</p>
            <p>The Parliament did then claime, and ſince have claimed, a Right to determine all controverſies that may ariſe in the Nation and that of right they might diſpoſe of the Militia of the Kingdome as they ſhould ſee cauſe; for in the Houſe of Commons vertually the power of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is for to make Lawes, or repeale Lawes, and to be the finall judges. It is true, the King held a confirming voyce, and was intruſted with the Militia and the Regall power, for the protecting and adminiſtring ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice unto the people, but when the Parliament ſaw a danger of the Kings converting that power to their and the truſters diſtruction, they tooke upon them the diſpoſall of the Militia, upon which the King broke with them and made a war.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:164983:6"/>
            <p> God having now given ſucceſſe to their cauſe, and inveſted them and their aſſiſters with full power, it now lieth upon them, to make good all promiſes, if poſſible, the leſſer giving way to the greater, and as much as in them, lyeth, indeavour to prevent future diſputes and quarrells, for the welfare of poſterity; and to ſettle the government of the Nation: So that the Regall power in what forme ſoever, may be ſubject to the Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and likewiſe to untwiſt thoſe lines of bondage, which will queſtion our juſt proceedings, there is no rational man that will imagine it unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, that the Parliament ſhould proceed to the ſetling the Kingdoms peace and Freedom without the King, ſeeing that after the conquering his Forces, and ſo many addreſſes, he will accept of nothing but what ſhall be agreeable to his will; the which muſt be a giving up the right of our cauſe, and advantage to the name and thing King, to recover all power in ſhort time, and to the winding of the Nation into worſe bondage and ſervitude then ever, to the will of the Prince, which will of neceſſity bee our portion, if there be not a cleare vindicating of the Rights and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the people, in the Legiſlative power; which was the maine thing contended for; and it is evident, that the ſupream power next un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, is inherent in the multitude, and that there is no juſt authority, but what is immediately derived from God himſelf by divine appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or mediately given from the people by their Repreſentative, who of right are not ſubject to any particular perſon or perſons; but may up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on grounds of common ſafety, alter Magiſtrates or Government, make new Lawes, or repeale old: Aboliſh Courts, or ſet up new, without the concurrence of King or Peeres. However this be caled new Doctrine or Levelling, it will appeare that in this is laid the foundation of the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of a Nation, in ſtating their Repreſentative free and equall, inveſted with full power, the perſons changeable ſucceſſively, ſo that whatſoever Lawes or Burdens the people bring upon themſelves, they will be of their own chuſing; whatſoever cuſtome is held contrary herto is a fruit of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt kept by force, and may juſtly be by force repelled. This is no change of principles, as is evident from the firſt conteſt. The peoples ſafety ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued the ſupream Law, and the Houſe of Commons iudges of that ſafety and interpreters of Law and they affirming the Kings oath binding him to confirme what Laws they chuſe, the Commons telling the Lords they ſhould indevour to ſave a people without them, if they would not concur.</p>
            <p>But it may be obiected, that the Ingagement at the firſt undertaking of the war, declared for King and Parliament, and that the Parliaments Declaration in the yeare 1646, declareth, for the maintaining of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:164983:6"/>of this Kingdom, by King, Lords, and Commons, and that the Proteſtation and Covenant of this Kingdom and <hi>Scotland,</hi> ingageth them to maintain the Kings authority, and that they have no thoughts or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions to diminiſh his Maieſties iuſt power and greatneſſe.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that men are bound by Conſcience and Honour, to make good all Ingagements ſo far as iuſtly they may, and if men be not found conſtant to their principles, no man can wiſely put confidence in them, nor truſt them farther then neceſſity inforceth. It will not be amiſſe to look over our former Ingagements, and moderately to conſider what may be performed, and what not. For indeed, they are ſo interwoven that it will be a difficult matter to make good every particular. Therefore firſt conſider the moſt generall things of greateſt importance, and make good them with as much proviſion for particulars, as generall will permit. And in the firſt place, that Intereſt of the peoples freedom muſt in Iuſtice take place: For in all Declarations, Papers, and Covenants, it hath been the chiefe thing pretended, and there never paſſed any promiſe of intruſting the King, but in order to the peace, freedom, and ſecurity of the Kingdom; and I beleeve it was expected, that when the Kings powers ſhould be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, he would have accepted the Parliaments conditions, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing, is a iuſt ground to alter their promiſes, and to proceed to the ſetling the Kingdom in freedom, ſafety, and peace, without the King: the which can never probably be done, without altering the former cuſtome in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Law. For whatſoever is acted upon the former conſtitution, will run to the King for confirmation; ſo there will be no ſecurity, unleſſe ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Parliaments Ordinances good Laws, and ſo conduce one Eſtate, and take away the thing King, which name the antient <hi>Romans</hi> could not indure for the ſpace of 400. yeares; and it will be found no ſmall let to the ſettlement of our peace. For it muſt be time that muſt produce ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from him and his poſterity: the Army muſt not be a protection for ever, neither will the people indure this Parliaments perpetuity, for the continuance of either longer then neceſſity inforceth, is inconſiſtent with the peoples freedome.</p>
            <p>And now the Souldiery having contracted much of the buſineſſe of the Kingdom upon their Shoulders, you will be put upon the exerciſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, you have already ſhown your ſtrength and valour in ſubduing the Forces that have oppoſed us; and if you can now find wayes to ſecure your ſelf and our aſſiſters, from the Authorities we have reſiſted, you will appeare much like a compleat man in Reaſon.</p>
            <p>J beſeech you Sir, looke back to the firſt Ingagement of the Parliament
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:164983:7"/>with due conſideration, and indeavour what you may, to procure the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance thereof. At the firſt rayſing an Army, The Parliament decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it to be for the deſence of the Proteſtant Religion, the Lawes of the Land, the Kings perſon, the priviledge of Parliament, the peoples juſt Rights and freedome; theſe things are ſpacious, and were never ſtated and publiſhed what is meant hereby. Some underſtand the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to be the Book of Common prayer for Worſhip the Epiſcopacie for Diſcipline, and the thirty nine Articles for Doctrine: But it Religion be taken in ſuch formes, then is it in a great meaſure altered by the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, in part with the Parliaments approbation, impoſing the Directory for Worſhip, the Presbytery for Diſcipline, and the Confeſſion of Faith, which they have publiſhed, for Doctrine; and in ſtead of Reſorming, have introduced Schiſme. It cannot be denyed but we were very zealous for the promoting of Religion, and I hope ſtill are; but I feare we did not rightly underſtand what Religion is. Certainly, Religion in the moſt generall acceptation, is that profeſſion of Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which a people hold forth to the world: in the former ſenſe it is moſt probable, that which we call Religion, was underſtood, and that which was then intended by the generall party of the Nation, was a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of what might appeare corrupt, and to free the people from thoſe burdens in Ceremonies impoſed, which many tender Conſciences could not beare. But now that which we call Religion, appears to me on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a traditionall formall profeſſion, and is made uſe of only to gain parties and Factions, under the ſpecious pretence of Religion, thereby to gain power to riſe in Dignities, for profit and honour among men. This is the Religion of <hi>Rome</hi> as at this day, pure State policie, in which is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended the depth of the myſtery of iniquity. Such is the Religion of the Turke, and many other Nations a meer emptie forme, in which nothing of the power of God is; and what is this alteration of Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Worſhip, and Doctrine which ſome men ſo furiouſly purſue, but the cloathing of Antichriſt with a new coat, changing out of one forme of the myſterie of iniquity into another. But it you ſeriouſly conſider, you may underſtand, that Religion is not a name, but a thing; not a forme, but a power, not a notion, but a ſubſtance divine: Religion conſiſteth in faith, and workes of righteouſneſſe; Religion is properly that inward power in the ſoule of a man, whereby be beleeveth, and is bound to God in righteouſnes and holineſſe; the demonſtration thereof, maniteſt in acts of Juſtice and mercy, viſiting the fatherleſſe and the widow, and keeping unſpotted from the world; ſo much of this power a man hath, ſo much
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:164983:7"/>Religion, where there is none of this power, there is no Religion; <hi>To as many as beleeve in Jeſus Chriſt, to them giveth he power to become the Sons of God.</hi> Now Sir, if there be a defending of the Proteſtant profeſſion, let men take it in what forme they underſtand. I beleeve it will be the beſt and ſafeſt making good this Ingagement Religion is not propagated by any humane power: the Civill Magiſtrate may protect Chriſtians in religious exerciſes, but to compell an externall Uniformity by a coerſive power, ſeeing there is no pretended infallibility will be prepoſterous, and more Antichriſtian then is the Pope himſelf. Chriſts Kingdom is ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and propagated only by the ſpirit in the adminiſtration of the word, without the help of humane force. If the Civill Magiſtrate exerciſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall juſtice, and tollerate religious exerciſe, it will be as much as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians will deſire.</p>
            <p>As for the Lawes of the land, which we are ingaged to defend, I think there are very few underſtand what they are in generall: we defend the lawes, if we act according to the ſupreame ends thereof, which is to ſave the people, and preſerve proprietie, and diſpence impartiall Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; and let the law have its courſe in Courts till there be a juſt alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. But if any thing appeare contrary to theſe ends by the judgement of the law-makers, it can be no breach of this ingagement, to alter the ſame.</p>
            <p>The third particular, was for the defence of the Kings perſon and the voyce went for the King and Parliament. But it ſeemed a ſtrange partadox to many, how we ſhould fight for the King, fighting againſt his perſonall commands, accompanied with his perſon, the beſt conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on J could make thereof, was the reſcuing him from his evill councel, that led him to the ruining himſelfe and the Nation, and we ever made him meerly paſſive, ſeduced by evill Councel, but it appeareth that his Followers rather acted his councel, then he theirs, but ſeeing he is ſtill in ſafety, it can be no breach of this ingagement, if his perſon be kept from deſtruction.</p>
            <p>The next particular is the priviledges of Parliament, and it were very good the people knew what they are, unlimited privilidges may prove as deſtructive as unbounded prerogative; it is reaſon they ſhould be cleared and declared that future Parliaments may be preſcribed, likewiſe for their ſitting and ending, that they may not wrong poſterities: and when they are rightly ſtated according to reaſon, no queſtion, but wee ſhall make good this ingagement ſo farre as may ſtand with the peoples free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:164983:8"/>
            <p> The fiſt thing, called the liberty of the ſubject, which is the only thing that can ſtand in competition, which the Prince muſt of neceſſitie be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured from oppreſſing tyrants, which can no better wayes be done then by giving all authority from their repreſentative, to whom all ought to be accountable, they being changable by an unalterable decree, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this once ſetled, we may ſafely involve all in this common bottome of Parliaments; unleſſe this be procured, we have done nothing for po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie; and I dare affirme, we had better have continued under arbitrary tytrany, then have contracted this miſerie and oppreſſion that the people have ſuffered, and ſtill lyeth upon them.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, that which hindreth our peace, is pride and coveteouſneſſe; which are the roots of all grand evils and miſchiefs, the great men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend which ſhall be greateſt, profit and honour blind the eyes of the wiſe, the people are divided upon theſe two heads, the King, and the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to which parties are contracted, and the way to compoſe is not compulſion, but by conviction, it is mercy and lenity conquers more up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on iugenious ſpirits, then auſterity and force: it would not be amiſſe to procure what ſhal be done, for or with the King, for it is againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments declared principles to keepe men in priſon, any longer then ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie enforceth, untill they may have a Judiciall try all, and ſeeing wee have been under ſuch bondage, that the conſtitution hath provided no Judicature to judge the King, and indeed he is not legally ſubject to the penall lawes. it will be moſt ſafe therefore to referr him to divine juſtice which will judge righteouſly, and to ſettle the government of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for quietneſſe ſake, with as much favour to the Prince, as the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſafety will permit. But as he ſticketh to his former principles and parties, there can be no truſting him with power, without giving up your cauſe, and ſubjecting your ſelves to the mercy of his will: he may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to the enjoyment of a ſufficient revenue, beyond any particular perſon, with his wife and children to a condition of freedome, ſafety, and peace, the publique ſafety being firſt provided for, and may be intruſted with power if afterwards inveſted therewith from a future repreſentative, in whom the fountaine of authority among men, juſtly is, and then can there be no deny all of being accountable thereto: Thus may the people be ſecured from tytrany.</p>
            <p>The Covenant which hath been inſiſted upon for pollitique ends, and ſtill is much preſſed by the Scots, J beleeve, may be ſtuck to till the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters diſſert it without any forced conſtruction, for thein ſweareing an utter extirpation of popery, prelacy, with all dependance on that hirarchy.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:164983:8"/>It will neceſſarily follow, that all coerſive power inforcing an externall uniformitie, muſt be taken away, for this is the foundation of popery, this is that ſpirit that ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhewing it ſelle to be God, <hi>and exalting it ſelfe above all that is called God,</hi> by making lawes to binde the conſcience in matters of faith.</p>
            <p>And by the extirpation of the prelacy with all depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on that Hierarchie, will the ordination of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie received from them become null: For their dependance is on that Hierachy from whence they had their inſtitution, to the office of the miniſtry The Prelates dare not preſſe this argument, becauſe of giving advantage to their adverſaries of <hi>Rome,</hi> from whence they had their own ſending theſe two arguments from the beſt interpretation of the Covenant will eaſily beat them oft from that hold, we may juſtly defend the government of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> againſt any that ſhall inforce any thing upon them contrary thereto, either in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, diſcipline or worſhip: we may likewiſe endeavour to bring the Churches of God in the three Kingdomes, to as neare a conformitie to the word and the example of the beſt Reformed Churches as is poſſible, ſtill provided there be no humane force or power, exerciſed to this purpoſe, the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of the chriſtian warfare are ſpirituall, not carnall, but mighty in operation to the deſtroying of ſpirituall wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in high places, to the bringing of the thoughts and imaginations of mens hearts into ſubiection, according to the mind and will of God. If conſcientious people were but united upon this principle, it would take off all cifferences in relation to ſpirituall things.</p>
            <p>Having taken this boldneſſe to write to you of matters of ſuch general concernment in relation to the publique. Give me leave to offer my thoughts in relation to the late tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action of affaires betweene the Army and the Parliament, which are but ſtifled for the preſent, and will queſtionleſſe break forth to the cleare juſtification of the Army, and thoſe members of Parliament that came to them or otherwiſe make them culpable, and juſtifie thoſe Members that ſate with Mr. <hi>Pellam.</hi> The Breach between them and us, was managed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:164983:9"/>by the major part of the Houſe, whoſe commands we diſobeyed upon juſt grounds, but came not to a reſiſtance till our way was made more cleare, by that outrage in the City Tumult, which made the Speakers and our friends fly to us for ſuccour. After which there remained neare ſix ſcore in and about <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and not above ſeventy came to the Army: Now without queſtion, the intereſt of the Houſes Authority remained with thoſe at <hi>London.</hi> For by the cuſtome of the Kingdom, the Houſe is included by fortie men, which keep their fitting according to its precedent adjournment, and they remaining, being the higheſt viſible authority in the Kingdom. The queſtion will be, by what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority we marched up to <hi>London</hi> in defiance to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, to the repelling of thoſe Hoſtile powers contracted by their Authority, and how the Army ſhall be juſtified or vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in ſuch proceedings.</p>
            <p>That which giveth me quiet and peace of Conſcience, is from theſe conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That when a Companie or Society of men, who are inveſted with power from God and nature to preſerve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the Authorities over them command things unjuſt, which will prove their ruin if obeyed. It is cleare to me, neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath no Law, they may appeale to Heaven and Earth to beare witneſſe to their cauſe, and betake themſelves to the prime Lawes of nature, to preſerve and defend themſelves, and may ſuppreſſe the Authority, if they perſiſt in proſecution of things deſtructive to the Communicie. I know no other way of breaking tyrannicall Uſurpations.</p>
            <p>Now it is moſt cleare, that the Parliament put the Army upon conditions which would have proved their ruin, if they had yeelded to their will. For if they had renounced their juſt Petition, and ſwallowed that abominable Declaration, and disbanded, they had been caſt upon their enemies mercy for their Indempnity, and to have truſted thoſe that had acted by ſecret Councels with the King, for ſetling the Rights and Freedome of the Nation which we had contended for.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The conſideration of the unequall Elections and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:164983:9"/>Conſtitution of the Houſe of Commons not repreſenting the maior part of the Nation, but Elections diſtributed according to the will of the King and his predeceſſors, ſo that thoſe who did not conſent, were only bound by a power of force, and the maior part not conſenting, are not oblieged when there being come in competition.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Houſes departing from their firſt integrity of communicating impartial Juſtice, &amp; by vertue of that act of continuance during pleaſure, grew into parties and Factions, and neglected to ſettle the government of the Kingdom, in order to the period of their ſitting, but rather its probably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to be perpetuall Dictators, ſo as to deprive the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that changeable Law making authorities which are the conſervators of their Liberties, to mantain all arbitrary in themſelves; this may iuſtly be charged upon the prevalent par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that were our oppoſers, who ſecretly carried on a combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to comply with the Kings intereſt to a more univerſall inſlaving the people then formerly.</p>
            <p>Having conſidered all proceedings of the moſt materiall concernment, it will neceſſarily come to this iſſue, that we have diſobeyed, reſiſted, and repelled all the Authoritie and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Kingdom, both King, Parliament, and all bounds of Law; and the authorities and government being bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, it is wholly diſſolved, and involved into its originall Fountain next under God the people. And the higheſt autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that is now viſible is the force of the Sword. For there is no reaſonable man, but will conclude the Parliament to be under a force, mixed of two parties, that have been in oppoſition, one while one partie is the Parliament, another while the other, even to which the ſtrongeſt power is contracted, ſo the ſtream runs, for at the time we lay at <hi>Brainford,</hi> your ſelf, and Son in Law <hi>Ireton</hi> affirmed in my hearing, that thoſe which remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> with Mr. <hi>Pellam,</hi> were no Parliament, but ſome Gentlemen claiming a Parliamentary Authority. And in our Remonſtrance from <hi>Kingſton,</hi> we declared to the world
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:164983:10"/>they were Uſurpers and Intruders, and that we would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thoſe who had voted to make a new warre upon us, to ſit there as ours and the Kingdoms Iudges; yet ſince they have been acknowledged to be a Parliament, and ſit here in Court to this day, and for what I know, are the chiefe fomenters of our diſtractions, and the Protracters of the redreſſes of the common grievances of the Nation. Now Sir, ſo long as that Remonſtrance from <hi>Kingſtone</hi> ſtands owned, J doe not conceive the Army concluded under the authority of the Houſe, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſetting the Houſe as a skreene between them and the fiery fury of the people in the midſt of the common grievances and diſtractions, and do yeeld obedience to the Parliament in what they command agreeable to your own judgement. And on the other hand, the Parliament and Synod, with all the Presbyterian party, with the <hi>Scots</hi> Councel, are indeavouring to get a power to bring you under the Laſh, and you can look for no other, but that if they get you and the Army down, they will pay you and your accomplices for their diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Therefore take care to uſe your reaſon and your power to ſecure your ſelves, not only from the King and his Lawes which he ſtill fighteth by, but likewiſe from the Parliament <hi>Pellamites,</hi> and their Ordinances, which you and the Army have ſlighted.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, I profeſſe for my own part, J am not over carefull J ſhall only uſe meanes to the diſcharge of my duty according to my judgement and reaſon, and whether I be any thing or nothing, it matters not; yet it behoves me to take care for the ſecurity and welfare of thoſe poor Souldiers under my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, which I have indeavoured to ingage in this common cauſe, which I vindicate, and ſhall by Gods aſſiſtance ſeale with my blood, by ſuffering if called thereunto. I value my reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as a man to ſtand in competition with my livelihood, but I value my principles more then life naturall, and before I would violate my conſcience in matter of concernment upon mature conſideration, I would ſuffer all the torment that men and Divels can invent.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:164983:10"/>
            <p> Now Sir, to ſecure your ſelf and friends, which is the chief work that lieth before you, I muſt needs ſay, I ſee no other way but by entring upon ſome way equivolent to that preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the paper, intitled <hi>The Agreement of the people.</hi> There is a neceſſity of ſetting a period to this Parliament, and change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the currant of the Law out of the Kings name, into the Commons, without which I can ſee no ſure ſecurity, but by making up your Intereſt under the King, and receiving In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnity and pardon from him: which laſt I doe deteſt, and ſhall ever labour to prevent. If any man can hold forth any other way wherein there is a probability to obtain ſecurity, freedome, and peace, Ile acknowledge my own weakneſſe, and give God thanks for raiſing up an Inſtrument for my convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I know the proſecution of the former is very dangerous and deſperate, the King, <hi>Scots,</hi> and forraign States will be our Enemies, yet if you fall back you muſt expect ruine; and if you go forward, you can be no worſe in the greateſt hazzards: and it is better periſhing in right wayes then in wrong.</p>
            <p>Having thus freely diſcovered my principles, and offered my deſires to your view, I muſt confeſſe my inabilities of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your knowledge in things of this nature, but looking upon you as a perſon of power and intereſt I thought good to diſcharge my mind, and to let you know, I ſhall not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to exerciſe force for the procuring things of this nature, but only plead at oportunities in wayes of reaſon, and ſhall ſtand by thofe that ſtand for the publique intereſt of the Nation, and ſhall upon a cleare way and call ingage my life as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, againſt ſuch as ſhall indeavour to deſtroy honeſt, peaceable men, by wayes of force and violence. And if you as formerly, ſhall ſtill own the Jntereſt of honeſt people, and forbeare the exerciſe of rigor upon thoſe that are friends to your ſelf, and the Common wealth, then ſhall I be ready to hazzard my life for your preſervation, when you ſhall be caſt upon the greateſt extremitie in the midſt of your many enemies, for you may aſſure your ſelf all ſtorms are not over, and that late inſurrection in <hi>London</hi> is but a fruit of that councel which will endeavour to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:164983:11"/>raiſe more ſuch there &amp; in other places, who care not if they break all reines, and make way for that abomination that maketh deſolate, rather then let go their pride and ambition: you muſt expect the further exerciſe of your faith &amp; patience in the times of tryal that are coming up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Nation. But the Lord inſtruct, keepe and preſerve you in the wayes of righteouſneſſe, ſhall be the prayers of him who deſires to ſerve you, while you ſerve the publique.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Francis White.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Colebrook</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aprill the</hi> 21. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
